hello and welcome to the first uh video
where we're going to start doing go
programming from scratch um this is
still a part of the holiday
boost um I realize the holiday boost has
been all over the place all of my boosts
are that's just the nature of trying to
adapt to the people that are watching uh
and participating in this stream and
overwhelmingly my community right now
has asked to cover go from scratch in
other words uh in fact in santis I'll
give them credit uh has pretty much
named my next book which is um what did
we say I can't even remember the exact
name now I have to go look at up again
but the the the the name will be
something along the lines of coding from
the
get-go and we are going to learn to
program from scratch Ino assuming you
don't know anything about programming
you know and we'll talk about what those
assumptions are and how to get going on
everything this hour however will be um
this hour will be dedicated to setting
up a go programming
environment and I think you should learn
go even if you know Java and JavaScript
I think go would be a great tool for you
to have on your belt um for lots of
reasons um
goes the primary language of cloud
native the world uh of enterprise
software maybe you heard kubernetes and
Docker and podman and Helm and terraform
they've all been written in go so
knowing how to read the code is
essential if you're going to be doing
that professionally um and It Go as a
much more approachable language when it
comes to programming because it's just
so much easier than Java or C uh Rob
Pike the one of The Adventures of go
calls go a Kinder gentler SE um and from
my personal experience I've you know
hundreds and hundreds of people that
I've helped uh most of the people who
learn go as a first language generally
prefer to pick up C or assembly as their
second language which I was not
expecting I was expecting that to not go
that way um I've taugh a lot of people
python is the first language and
JavaScript is the first language and I
haven't taught that many people go as a
first language so this will be exciting
for me as well because it'll give me a
lot more data points and um help us
establish whether whether go could be
potentially a viable replacement um to
AP Computer Science and Java which I
think it could be I really think it
could be it's got all the great things
that you want from a first language that
is not too easy and python I think is
too easy and therefore you don't learn
strict typing you don't learn uh
Anonymous functions you don't learn you
know first class function calls you
don't there's a lot of things you don't
you understand pointers at all um so and
and go is kind of the the perfect you
know um Goldilocks language for for
first for first languages in my opinion
and I I don't have a lot of data to back
that up uh there's really no way to do
that except for to try it so here you
are being my guinea pigs um so let's do
that let's go ahead and get started
setting it up and look at what it takes
now I for the most part obviously I'm
going to use the terminal you don't know
already I'm doing another book called
terminal velocity which covers all of
this stuff about getting fast and good
in the terminal I still think you should
learn it I still think programming go
from the terminal is the best way to do
it but this this assumption the book
itself and this video series right here
makes no assumptions about how you're
going to write the code we're going to
jump right into hello world and yes
we're going to do hello world because
reasons probably we'll call it hello
friend instead um and so we're going to
do how do I install go where do I get it
how do I set it up that's what the next
hour is about um I am going to cover two
or three ways for you to get go um based
on what you want to do so if you already
the first thing we want to talk about is
how do you get a uh a command line with
go so this is actually really easy um if
you're on a Mac it's Brew install
go uh I think it might be go Lang
actually so this is
um Brew
install okay so we go
1.234 uh something to know about go is
that once you install an an older
version of it you can use go itself to
grab the new one and um so let's go do
that let's go say so if you're on a if
you're on a Windows machine your windows
or
WSL uh it's a lot easier to do
that H there's couple good versions yeah
agreed so we're going to I'm going to
take you on to Linux um as
well uh listen from K connections oh
whoops I think this machine might be off
right now anyway if you're on a machine
that's got uh Linux my my Linux machine
is off right now didn't check it um and
so we're going to
uh yeah let's we're going to go do next
so if you are on a if you're on a a
machine Linux or Unix machine it would
just be sudu apt install go I think it
might be goang um you can do that if you
want to just install it on Windows
without using any of that other stuff
I'm pretty sure let me go let me go
check I have it in here I'm pretty sure
it's wi get install go let me just show
you uh so you know pause the video and
do what you have to do to get it on here
so here's here's the installer so Brew
it's Brew install goang Oro windows it's
wind get if it's it's get bash or if
it's windows or get bash you can do uh
wi get install go.go that will install
onto your you know host OS if your
windows um you can do sud app get
install while go for go link if you're
on wsl2 if you're on wsl2 uh or your you
know any any apt based uh Linux which
you should probably already know about
if you're going to get there um you
decide which one you need to do um you
can do go development on Windows
natively a lot of people do and they do
not use WSL and they do not use a
terminal so if that describes you you
want to do the install this way you can
always go out and download the installer
from the website and do it that way but
I strongly encourage people to use the
package managers they are just easier
they're just a lot easier to use U if
you don't know how to use a package
manager you probably want to look into
that stuff before you start getting into
coding really well that stuff is I I
cover that stuff in another book called
terminal velocity which which is all
terminal based so there that's that's
all we're going to say about that and
we're going to move forward um uh go the
go do whole world directly no I have to
explain this the my biggest pay PE
they're saying no we should just write
hello world I'm like nope not doing that
the reason I'm not doing that is because
I hate books that don't tell me how to
get the language to install it
okay it drives me nuts it drives me nuts
I hate that I've had that so many
languages okay what editor are you going
to use I'm going to be using Vim
specifically neovim using vimo and if
you want to use something else that's
fine it's not really within the scope of
this book I did want to show you one
other thing that you could do and get
set up but I'm going to go ahead and do
this a lot of you are going to want to
do this I don't like it but you can use
it okay we're going to actually I know
someone's going to give me a hard time
we're going to use vs code so um you can
just put vs code I think vs code is
already did I have it already installed
on here yeah so you go and download V
Studio code it's very popular there's
there's vs codium if you prefer I don't
care if you want to do with emac that's
fine too but here's the thing okay so we
have vs code installed on the computer
and we're going to be using get and get
Hub to save our source code which I am
going to be doing and so we're not going
to cover directly how to set up get GI
hub for that you have to do that in a
different a different video uh and you
know terminal velocity I cover that so
I'm assuming you have a GI up account
I'm assuming you know how to do get um
reasonably well and that you've already
authenticated on your command line okay
so but if you prefer you can do this so
the first step besides that we're going
to go ahead and close Visual Studio code
um I use vs code for go development I
really want to use Sublime for LSP
formatting yeah you can go you can do
however whichever when you want if you
do use vs code just a just a note make
sure that you install the go plugins in
fact Let Me Go call those up
um let me call it up again and see if I
can remember what they are I haven't
done this in forever so extensions let's
go do actually you know what let's not
do that I I know if you start working on
go code it will actually prompt you let
me show you so let's let's back up a
little bit so okay let's make uh a new
repo so I'm not covering this but you
need to find a directory to put this in
now hopefully if I were you I would make
a directory called repos in your home
directory uh and then inside of repos I
would put I cover this in terminal
velocity but github.com I would I would
suggest you make a directory structure
that matches the URLs so that you don't
have naming conflicts which I have had
in the past so you see I'm going to CD
into github.com you can do that from the
command line if you want instead I mean
from the web browser or whatever your
Explorer and then
my account here it is all right so I got
all this stuff here and you need to
create yourself a a repo that has the
stuff that you want to do here now you
can make this repo you can name it uh go
coding you can name it lab you can name
it whatever you want in my case I'm
going to call it um we're going to what
should we call it g repo create clone
private and let's let's call it
um uh GetGo let's see coding from the
get
go how about that and it's a big old
long one you probably want to call your
lab you if you want to put all of your
um stuff in a single repo like a lab
repo which I talk about in term of
velocity you can consider that there are
really two major um repos I think
everybody should have a DOT files repo
of some kind and a lab repo where you
can put your little exper exp and
document them as you want uh Some people
prefer to do that in you know Atomic
individual repos that's up to you in
this particular case because I'm making
a video and I want it to show up in the
in the in the name uh I'm going to go
ahead and and make a repo like that and
so now I've got this repo to go into
that um that I actually will make public
the more stuff that we put in here as we
go through this so if you can see what
I've done um something that is in the
preface of my book it talks about how
you're making your own textbook here
okay um I do have a book and I do plan
on having examples and all the solutions
and everything in there but it's really
really important that right from the
beginning that you start writing your
own book in fact I I've at a school for
you know almost almost 15 years and I've
never had a book because I've never
needed a book because everybody who's
there is writing their own book and it's
much more palatable it's much more
visceral you know pneumonic and
memorable whatever you want want to say
it's just easier for you to write your
own book um because then you can always
go back and you can add your own notes
wherever you want to and you're not like
you're not like you know dog leafing a
paperbook that you're not going to have
with you you can pull it up wherever you
are so so this is the book right now I
still will you know outline the things
that you should do but it' be more about
how to do them I mean more about this is
what you should do and stuff and then
it'll kind of send send you on your way
um just a reminder we're going to be
covering like really silly things from
scratch so if you're here because you
want to learn how to get good as a
hacker or as a cyy this is the wrong
place and I I labored that point pretty
heavily with my community because
because I you know part of me thinks
that you shouldn't learn go unless it's
to solve an actual problem and to learn
it we're kind of foregoing that for a
while to do something silly that you'll
remember um which you know is hard for
me because I a very practical person I
think you should you know use it for
actual things and and I probably still
will write another book called um go for
um you know go for Cy and hackers um you
know generating malware and goat which
is really great for that um so it it it
does okay so here we go um so we're in
this directory uh you can see where it
is C to my screen and we're ready to
start coding but what this is what I
wanted to show you so first of all okay
so my repo hasn't been committed yet I
need to put something simple in here so
uh you know you might not need to do
this but I do Branch DM uh main to
change the name uh I'm going to actually
add a readme file and what I wanted to
show you is I can actually edit the file
from right here in vs code with
codespace DOT uh do you trust wait
actually I want I don't want to do that
yet not yet just a second I want to
write my first go code here and then
you'll see what happens with vs code so
um let's actually just write the readme
file first uh say uh what do we want to
say we say
um uh learning what is
it uh get
code troll is Hello World in episode
two yes um hello world no we're going to
say uh coding from the GetGo
and just put a thing here get get add
dot get
commit add read
me uh get push Das origin main we're not
covering that in here that's a terminal
velocity thing um uh and push so that
will push it up um we already did that
so GH uh repo
uh view-- web we'll open my web browser
up to that P page and here we are so
we're ready to write a code here now I
want to show you a couple cool things
you can do here the first thing is from
the from this actual page you can push
Dot and it will open up vs code in your
web browser some of you may not know
that all right so the reason I'm showing
you that is because if you want to work
on your development
and you don't have a computer uh or
you're using a school computer or
something you can do it on
GitHub uh now obviously it's better to
have your own laptop with you but you
can do it here and you can come in here
and you could say I want to open up a
new file uh and actually let's just say
main.go we make a main.go file here and
hit enter and it didn't have anything in
here so package main we we'll get into
this a little bit later um but you can
go ahead and see how this it's got the X
up here that means it hasn't been saved
um you can change your automatic
settings here um
to uh there's there's one that will
automat Auto saave so let's go search
for us it's been a while since I use vs
code but let's try autosave so uh
control autosave of editors that have
unsaved
changes um on Focus change on window
change I guess on Focus change all right
so anyway
um yeah so it will actually save it and
it will um you know when you go back and
forth you should be able to have it
saved okay so since it did save it um
now I when I come back here I need to do
get pull don't forget that to get the
latest it doesn't look like it saved
it I don't use it from the terminal like
I don't do this very much so let's see
what happens oh right here I forgot here
we go so it's not saving it so right
here it's like it has something to be
saved I say uh add main main.go commit
and push so again you may not want to do
this I just want to show you that you
can do it okay um and now if I do get
pull uh that will pull down the latest
library and I have my main.go file here
and I can do that now in addition to
that so let's go ahead and close this in
addition to this if if you have vs code
on your computer you can just do code uh
codespace Dot and it will open up vs
code in the context of this project and
so it'll open up on your local computer
if you've installed it and it will put
it there and then you have to say do you
trust the authors of this folder yes I
trust the authors uh trust the files in
the parent folder yes okay and it's
giving you a bunch of stuff you can do
co-pilot all these other crazy things
that people love I don't really like any
of those those things but you can use
those if you want um and here we have uh
the welcome I bet shows you about how to
read about it how to get around the only
thing other thing about bs code you
probably need to know is how to open the
terminal which is um command
backtick uh is it control back tick
there we go so for uh it's control back
tick on a Mac uh I I don't know what it
is probably control back tick on Windows
as well uh that opens up a terminal and
you're probably going to want to do that
a lot okay uh that does open up a
terminal on your local computer um I am
kind of curious what that does on GitHub
so I'm going to go ahead and spend some
time trying that out right now we can
close the welcome we don't need that so
you know if I make a change here I can
say and uh okay that's what I was this
is what I wanted to show you so it says
here do you want to install the
recommended go extension from go uh at
go Google say yes I would please okay
and then it's going to put in the
extensions for for you uh go tools yes
get all the tools of course I already
have these already but it's putting them
in a special place that it likes
apparently so um it's installing GitHub
and this this actually does take quite a
while to do um but we're going to sit
through it and wait actually while it's
doing that why don't we go back to the
web page and
test um the GitHub repo github.com
rxr uh this is mine you can come on over
here and have this is my books by the
way um if you want to go see the books
that are over there and they're
perpetually being dealt with but if you
want to come check it out you can um but
um yeah so if we go
into uh the the the thing that I just
saved so if you click on my if you click
on my follow icon it should be on there
let me go see yeah there we go no that's
not me your profile all right here we go
where is it where's my last commit where
is it got Tempo show
activity two requests 10 repositories
Bonsai
persistance H I'm trying to find it I
can't find it I don't want have to type
it all over
here wait what was
it coding oh I made it did I make it
private C coding from the get go you're
right yeah okay so here it is
all right so here it is um all right so
now now we're going to
push uh hello hello World episode 3 are
you talking about Mr Robot yeah so we're
going to do dot again but I want to try
something I want to see if the terminal
can be open from here I doubt it I
seriously doubt it so control back tick
oh my
gosh you can create it let's see you can
create a terminal by continuing in an
environment that can run code uh your
working changes will come to you after
you turn on cloud changes spin up a
fully configured development envir
forain in the cloud using Code spaces
code spaces you have to pay for so that
will be a no uh clone this repo to your
local machine and vs code desktop okay
so that's what I was expecting um you
can't use the terminal to run your
program here without code spaces which
I'm pretty sure they're going to say I
have to pay for now to be fair I'm
already paying for code spaces
um usage paid for by blah blah blah no
I'm not doing that no I have a pro
account with go get but I don't want to
pay money just to run stuff that I can
run on my local
machine so yeah anyway that uh I'm glad
we went through that though because this
the point of this hour is to get set up
and get going um go forbs code version
whatever uh go to latest on Telemetry
uploading is off by default
good um all tools are successfully
installed in go okay so we can close
this and I think it's really cool about
this is it will show you all kinds of
like errors while while they're
happening um I'm gonna zoom in if I
remember right there we go I can zoom in
a little
bit um and give you guys some things I'm
obviously I'm going to spend most of the
time in the terminal I just I know that
some of you want to use this particular
your absolute beginers uh are not going
to be comfortable editing in the
terminal yet so if you're not you know
everything in the book and in these
videos you can do this way um if you
want if you want to do it this way okay
so U if you want to take the time to
learn a terminal that was a great time
but you don't have to do that um all
right so you see here you see this this
is what I'm going to show you see this
see the circle up here uh I have had so
many beginners lose their work because
they forget they don't set up Auto uh
save and that this means that you're not
being saved so what you want to do is go
down here and you click
on uh looks like they changed it back up
in sync
settings yeah I don't know where it is I
don't know where it is anymore looks
like they moved
it yeah that's not it and I don't how do
I get rid of it now I I do not like goey
interfaces please sign in and back up
your sync across devices did they make
that a part of us code now finally youed
to have to use a third party thing to
synchronize your
settings well okay I I'm learning stuff
about bs code but I don't know how to
get out people make complain about bi
not being able to exit I can't how do I
get the thing off the
screen I'll just close vs
code okay uh is it Escape seriously is
it actually Escape all right we'll try
it again I am not a gooey guy people I
don't I don't unless you're go web
developing I don't think it's a good I
think you should use a
terminal there I said it okay
um anyway what I want to try that again
okay backham is saying check for updates
no themes oh you can change your theme
this is my
most what I'm dealing with particularly
with young people they their favorite
thing they like about vs code is the
themes they I we'll lose like we'll lose
like 25 minutes just on the themes right
so you can actually download themes uh I
used to be a huge s Iz Dark fan I
actually like this in fact one Christmas
I wrote a whole bunch of um I I wrote a
whole bunch of code uh over Christmas
and I had this theme how's that for a
theme how's that for a Christmas shy red
the whole day it's actually really fun I
I I have a lot of good memories of
having this theme this like really
really red theme isn't that insane the
bare theme has a c really nice yeah
there's like a whole bunch of things you
can actually install your favorite theme
my favorite terminal theme is Grove boox
media
material
uh and here here I am already getting
distracted by
themes oh I'm such a bad you know what
solarized dark brings back so many
memories from the old days my this was
my colors of my company when I first
started I like the I like the bloody
theme I do like the red one it's like
it's Jolly to me it's jolly it's like
very festive
not to mention it's like going to be
totally if I put that red tee on it's
like people on YouTube are not going to
be able to look away it's like oh my
gosh what's going on with this
guy Fallout pit boy theme
obviously is there a Fallout Pip Boy
theme okay we got to find it we have to
find it seriously it's like okay to do
this impossible it's not actually yeah
I'm not going to do it for I promise I
won't do this okay this is a good time
for you me to show how to go look I do
this is the first time I've opened vs
code and done anything significant in 5
years so please forgive me okay please
forgive me because I have no idea what
I'm doing so there's the rest of the Go
stuff you can go add those you got your
AI programming viim
emulation no viim emulations doesn't
have doesn't have filter commands so
what's the point um anyway uh extensions
search for Fallout okay I'm going to
search for Fallout I wanted I want to
see this there's a what there's a
Fallout pit boy theme oh my
gosh it's almost looks like somebody
wants to use the terminal or
something yeah wait oh God how come it
went away I want it back I want it
back where'd it go where' it go I'm
going to go get it again am I taking way
too much time I okay here we go wow look
at how
pretty that's perfect now wow look how
pretty this is
oo do you guys want me to use the green
theme for for for my terminal too
instead of group box I can totally do
this I can do whatever you guys want I
should make it so that you guys can
change my theme that's a thing that
twitch streamers do and then so many
people hate it though because they're
like I can't read a thing all right just
use the default so the colors match yeah
I'm not look I'm not even using this
theme so the reason I got distracted is
because I was trying to show you to get
rid of this circle here see the circle
up there that means you're not getting
autosaved the only the only input I have
for you on vs code there's three pieces
of input for you okay so listen up put
them in your notes number one make sure
you you know how to Auto sa I've seen
people totally ruined by
this um number two make sure that you
know how to save to GitHub it's actually
built in it's right here you just click
on this and oops I'm showing balloons
because I'm yeah so you can actually go
here you type your thing and it auto
auto pushes to GitHub when I was using
when I was working with people who were
just starting out this is much easier to
teach a beginner uh than the command
line forget it's the same thing that hi
the same thing from you so you make
changes you put your little comment in
there and you click save and
everything's good and it's all
synchronized and it just works um so
again so make sure you know how to get
push and no make sure make sure you know
how to autosave make sure you know how
to get push and uh the third thing would
just be knowing how to open it from the
command line so if you are on the
command line and you want to open it
from any place you just put codespace
dot and that will open it up where
you're at so if you ever get lost you
can open you know what's really cool
about that is that that will actually
work even if you are in here let me show
you something really cool so like if you
if you know how to get around from the
command line and you want to go
someplace
else um lab sample two I guess you can
actually do this you can do code Dot and
it will actually update the current
active syntax and it will move it into
that other location um if you do
if uh I mean it will open it there if
you do I think it's code dash what is it
I forget which one it is I think it's
dashr uh let me see I'm trying to look
for the command there's a command reuse
there it is the r all right so if you do
this if you do code dasr dot it will
reuse the current window and it'll
reload that to be in it now it's doing
this because the other one didn't save
so I'm going to go and click save so
that reset and open to the new location
right so there was no project here or
anything so then I can do it again and I
can do go CD do do SL and I can go into
code what is it coding from the get-go
and I can do code dasr Dot and that'll
reset the syntax to the other one and
remember where it was and everything so
um you know I it even restored my
history that's kind of cool that's kind
of cool so anyway this that's this is
all you're going to get from me on vs
code you see here it says that it
doesn't have one saved right so I'm
going to click on that I'm going to say
uh some small
change and I'm going to click on Commit
and that's going to push it say do I
want to push it yes stage commits is a
different thing it's an intermediate
step you almost always want to say yes
to that but it'll give you all your
stuff here and you know you can always
go out to GitHub I think there's
actually a thing that will take you to
the GitHub of this page if you want to
go see it that way
um but you know that is the end of my vs
code introduction to you I am no longer
going to be using vs code but no shame
using vs code to get started if that's
your first thing there are professionals
who swear by vs code they use it all the
time for go development and every other
kind of development you can imagine um
don't let anybody else tell you you
can't use it um I might make I might
poke fun of it and make jokes and things
but deep down you use you will you do
what you want to do and whatever comes
easier for you and there's a guy who
gave a person that I mentored $100,000
starting salary and in his starting
interview um he was during the interview
the person used vs code and apologized
to the guy that was that he was
interviewing because he used BS code for
go programming and the guy being
interviewed who got the job um was using
Bim from the command line so you know
there's a certain Mystique with using
the terminal but that there's certainly
no requirement that you use the terminal
to do any development whatsoever but
that said that's all I'm going to say
because I am a terminal user always have
been I still think it's better and you
can make your own decision okay um make
sure you turn on autosave which I forgot
to do so let's go here programs settings
autosave uh Autos save delay after delay
auto workpace file
controls auto save up editors of having
un
changes after lay on Focus
change after
delay I it looks like they changed it it
used to be there was just a setting
actually looks like they got rid of the
setting oh there it is never mind I take
it back this is such an important
setting God they didn't change it that's
makes me happy all right
so guys this is where it is it's under
it's under uh right here here this is it
it's a menu it's a
menu uh un resolve issues and couldn't
handle it 6 just uh vs code M A lot of
people like that vs code Vim so I spam
it all the time yes uh the top of the
screen is cut off oh okay it's the file
menu so it's file menu go to the file
menu and find the Autos sa thing and
turn that on okay that will set you up
an autosave for now um there are a lot
of advantages the vs code over other
things for example um uh read me so
here's kind of a cool Advantage um you
can have uh so this is a a markdown file
and you can actually preview the
markdown right here while you're taking
your notes so if that's the kind of
thing you want to see um you know you
can do that you can say uh you know
first
item uh Second and we haven't learned um
markdown yet we learned that in terminal
velocity so we I kind of expect you to
know markdown already to take your own
notes to write your own book either in
asid do or in uh markdown so you should
know you should definitely know markdown
but if you want to go the extra mile you
can learn asky do write your own books
and stuff um that's all cover covered in
terminal velocity I am not covering that
at all right now if you do not know
markdown and you proceed make sure you
allocate time to to learn markdown so
you can take your own notes because how
else are you going to write about it if
you don't want to write it in markdown
you want to write regular text that's
also fine but here's why it's better to
do this because then you can do this
right and you can actually take your
little note here and by the way if you
use asky do for this you can include
your source code in your notes it's kind
of cool um I'll do a whole thing on that
so for right here you can just say
package
main ah and you see how it kind of does
the thing right so import uh
fmt uh we're going to we're going to
cover this in just a second
so um oops it AO added a stupid thing I
hate it when it does
that yeah we're doing the first exercise
already
but hello
world all right so you can see how it
kind of syntax highlights where you can
get the pre preview of it um and in
obsidian you can yes there's obsidian
other things have Integrations you can
run the code blocks if you want to um
you don't need to do that here at all
though um so anyway um this is also
showing you if you have problems so like
if you uh forget a thing uh and well so
far it's not showing me the problems oh
it's because it's marked down never mind
derp anyway I was just showing you the
previewing if if you um oh look okay it
didn't autosave what's going on there
oh look at that autosave I have to turn
autosave on okay I turned Autos save
just don't forget
autosave don't forget it's autosave my
friends all right so so let's we close
this let's go back over here let's go
open main. go so if you if you write
something wrong in here you should start
to see errors and stuff fmt okay so it's
telling you what the error is and if you
hover over it it tells you what the
problem is and how to fix it um you can
format un save yes you you certain can
so there there are a lot of people who
think that that using a full-blown even
if lightweight IDE like this is the way
to go um there there's a better one is
um I've heard I've never used it once um
is go land but you have to pay um and so
there a lot of people like the idea of
like all the help that they're getting
and and the the the you know the code
spaces integration and and and um you
know all of that and if that's your
thing that's cool that's that's that's
fine it's totally fine I I there's no
problem there um but um you know I'm not
going to do that okay so it Go line is
almost too powerful it changes all the
Imports at the top depending on whether
you're using that I think it needs to do
that any good editor will do that uh
doeses this not do that if this doesn't
do that I'm going to be very sad one of
the hardest things to maintain and go is
all the imported packages because they
have to be there and um we're going to
do hell world again I promise we'll
explain the whole thing in just a sec so
now when I save this I'm I'm trying to
use VI to save and it's not working
because I don't have been bindings on
here this is kind of yeah there we go
okay thank God so it does pull it in any
any editor you use if it doesn't
automatically update your Imports you'll
want to
you shoot yourself in the head I mean
it'll be like crazy so you definitely
want the Imports to be automatically
imported when they're used when you stop
using them when you save it gets rid of
them so that's those are some things to
consider in your Ide at the end of the
day there's really only four main idees
a Vim or Neo which I count as one um you
know vs code
goand and uh emac and I don't I've never
met a single emac programmer who
programs and go I I know they probably
exist I've never met one so um those are
your options and you can make that
decision um and at that point we're
we're pretty much done okay so the next
thing we're going to do is we're going
to talk about we we've got another we
got another 10 10 or 20 minutes to talk
and I want to show you how to start a
project okay so we already know how to
get to the terminal right there are
certain things in go that you have to do
from the terminal
um and I it's so whether you're doing it
from BS code or you're doing it from
another terminal separately you know
that's the thing I think you can
actually automate these things to build
on their own um in fact I think there's
probably something under here that does
this okay so there's your
tools I think you could probably have it
set um as go play there's probably some
tools to do this that I I know there are
because I used to have them but um that
will automatically build your code
anytime you make a change um and I you
can decide how many I'm not going to go
down the plug-in path with you if you
want to go do those things you can but
we do I'll stay over here since we're
already here but let's go ahead and do
the first commands for initializing your
directory structure so um a lot of books
that are teaching you go will not have
you do what I'm going to have you do but
I think it will make it easier for you
um
what we're going to do is we're going to
immediately begin with something called
a go module um it's completely possible
to write go without using modules at all
but it's very unlikely that in any
professional capacity uh or any capacity
where it mattered you would ever do this
so I think you should learn to code to
start by starting up a a a thing uh
first oh look Let's uh always update oh
boy it's doing all kinds of things is it
is it all is it updated already go PLS
that's the language server in case you
don't know no problems have been
detected in your workspace debug
console I lost my my thing though where
am I I want I want my console
again where did my console
go all right there we go I did the I did
my control uh back tick and it worked
again all right so here we are we're
back in our command line and so the
First Command you should do is go mod in
it and this just initializes a new
module creates a go dood file and we are
now going to give it a name now um this
gets interesting right
because
um we'll get into go modules much much
later uh but right now just you can use
any name but what I would do is I would
use the same name as your git repo yes
but you don't have to do that so in this
case we would say github.com rvx Rob
coding from the
Geto and as a general rule you should
just always do this in fact I you know
unless you're doing some really black
hat stuff you don't want anybody to ever
see then you know you you would you
would always put the name of your GitHub
repo private or otherwise in your go mod
and it statement right it is I do want
to say for the black hats out there and
the cyber security people that if you
prefer to not do this you can put
whatever you want here and if you do
that I would suggest sticking with a
common domain name within your own
private um uh structure but the thing to
take away from this is that go itself
has not added an additional ecosystem
system for you know registering packages
and reusing code the same way node has
done or Pearl with cpan or even python
you know all of these other languages
have these extensive you know
massive
uh whatever repositories of code where
you can use them and one of the smartest
Things That Go did is they decided to
reuse the existing systems of the world
uh specifically any of the git systems
or SN any of the existing Source
management uh tools that exist thereby
allowing any git repo to to work any
place that you can put a git repo any
address that resolves on your
network as long as it's pointing to a
git repo doesn't even have to be a
website it can just be available over
SSH or whatever
can be used as a module okay that's all
I'm going to say about that we're going
to revisit that later but it's important
that you get this type um there are a
couple of configurations that you're
going to want to add to your terminal
which I'm going to show you right away
that are going to speed up your
development quite a bit and we're going
to go ahead and do that right now um
after we do this so let's do go we have
a few minutes left so let's do go mod
tidy so go mod tidy is going to bring in
uh any of your dependencies it's a good
habit to get into to do go mod tidy
anytime you change a dependency on
something right now you don't have any
dependencies but you will and when you
do you definitely want to do that
otherwise you're unnecessarily going to
be porting around a bunch of uh code
that'll get pulled down and get unused
uh without Goan tidy I don't know why
they don't do that automatically I think
it would have be nice but they don't do
that so um okay so based on that uh
there are a couple of other things to
keep in mind so so if you want to look
at your environment variables for go and
we're not covering what environment
variables are uh right now we will cover
variables later but what these go
environment variables kind of they're
like settings for go to tell it what to
do right and you can change the settings
that's what a variable is um but if you
go go EnV and you hit enter you're going
to see a bunch of
Flags uh a bunch of settings you know
with the equal sign and these are all
called envir enironment variables and
whether on Windows or Mac or WSL it'll
be the same um uh speed up
what yeah you don't know to we're going
to do hello world this hour has just
been setting up go that's the only thing
this hour is about okay so um there's a
couple of settings here that you you
might want to look at and this is where
we get a chicken in the egg situation
right because um to tell you the truth
you kind of need to know how to
configure your shell
before you can code and go and that
whether it be Windows or Mac or Unix or
Linux if you don't know how to configure
your system you're going to have a hard
time writing go code it's like this
whole chicken in the egg thing but you
don't you don't know how to code yet so
you may not have even known what a
variable was and now I'm telling you you
got to set a variable before you can
learn about what a variable is right so
I understand that this is frustrating
but you know we'll see if we can get
through it so here here are the
different things here so it tells you
all the different things you got going
on and there's a couple of settings here
that I'm just going to mention before we
leave and um it tells you the go mod
where your go work is what it's getting
compiled with and
stuff um but there are some important
ones that you probably don't need to
mess with as a beginner but I just want
to mention
them uh you want your down voting Bob R
go are you going to down vote me I hate
you um all right so if we go
to where is
go private I don't see
it you guys see
it this is interesting this this this
version in vs code is totally different
than than the one that's on my command
line I it's totally different you guys
yeah let me show you that's cool I
didn't know that all right so let me go
in
here
so see here it says has has the go path
right
loo
and let's see what else we
have I'm looking for
local he seems it is a virtual
environment for go yeah that's that's
new it didn't used to do that so I'm
glad I did
that yeah I think it is making a virtual
environment but I'm not
sure are there issues with the order or
sequence of those variables no no these
are just getting dumped out the order
doesn't matter
um yeah I I I'm well let me okay pardon
me for a second while I show you my
my here we go
yeah no
proxy go proxy direct EnV wait go
EnV go
proxy direct okay was that set and I
didn't see it that's the one I wanted
you guys to
see okay so what that does
is oh it's there there it is okay it is
there all right let me go back on the
other one and see so is go proxy here
too okay I set this one by default I
don't think you can set
it can you set it by going here and just
clicking on a thing you can look at that
look at that you guys look at
that yeah you can click on this and say
I want to make a new one look at this
this is fun look at you look at you can
just click on it and go do it go no
proxy they got rid of G proxy G proxy
direct okay there it is if go proxy is
not direct go change it to direct all
right so um it looks like mine is
picking up my environment after all I
was just having a hard time seeing I
totally this none of these tools were
there when I used go in the VSCO before
so we need more places with EnV yeah um
so this is kind of cool because if
you're a beginner and you don't know
what variables are you just know to go
change the setting right I want to go
change my setting so just change change
that one to direct and that'll probably
wrap up this video um what does it do
okay so let me just talk to you about
that what that setting does really quick
um I searching for proxy so you can just
do go no proxy as well if you set goo
proxy to true or whatever it actually
you can set goo proxy to a specific
domain so like if you have I mean
there's so many of these things we can
spend all day talking about all the
settings you can have but what I need to
just tell you is about how this works
right so um your your go your go proxy
is sets at proxy gang. direct yeah go
proxy equals proxy go all right so I
would I would change it to okay let me
let me tell you what it does all right
so the the by
um yeah
show all the go environment variables
yes okay so what what it by default
because go didn't want to depend
on you know just GitHub being up uh or
anything they the Google uh and the the
go Lang Foundation uh go is obviously
it's a it's a Google controlled project
that is 100% open source this is a
problem for a lot of people but it's
actually usually a really great thing
because Enterprises tend to adopt things
that are that have that level of support
whether you like it or not I'm just
telling you that's the way it is um even
though the people that invented it also
invented Unicode and Unix so you know
it's a good thing bottom line they
needed to have a way to make it so that
people could get to uh this code that's
being sourced out there but they didn't
want to do that registry that big old
registry you put all the stuff in right
so what they made is they made these
proxy servers and they're controversial
because yes they are copies they contain
copies of the full package go modules
that you're depending on and they get
downloaded and they go through there and
stuff but the reason you don't want it
is because uh when you're doing
development right now the main reason
you don't want it is because it takes
too much time to propagate a lot of
times you like you you won't get this
problem right away because we we're not
going to use modules right away but
eventually you're going to start to want
to turn around changes faster and you're
not going to see your changes because
they have to be proxied to the caching
servers and they have to do all this
thing so it take even though it might
take you longer if you set direct
because it has to go straight to the
source whether it's GitHub or Source Hut
or whatever it still has to go straight
there and get it and you're guaranteed
to always get the latest um if you do
anything internally on a VPN um like uh
like you're working you know for a
company or something uh there's a strong
possibility you're going to need to use
direct as well if you're hosting
anything on internal servers or if
you're doing what worse if you're using
inner source which is a whole model of
you know using Enterprise Cloud without
Enterprise Cloud which is this Total
video by itself um by the way if you I
do you know I regularly code go at work
using these two different models and
have hit a number of problems with each
of those and worked around them um and
and I'm just telling you in advance
before we wrap up the video that if
you're here this long and you want to
talk about any of those specifics about
how your development environment is set
up to work maybe somebody's asking why
are we not doing this in a container and
actually that's a good thing to do right
as we wrap up we only have seven minutes
left um if you want to just play around
with go and you don't want to mess with
anything else and you know how to use
containers you can just spin up a go
container and start coding like right
now and let me show you how to do that
okay so that's the last option that that
I want to show so I'm going to use pod
man uh if you want you guys already know
how to mount directories and stuff if
you know if you know these kinds of
things um but I'm not going to mount
anything because I I don't want that
right um so I'm just going to do
podman uh run it and remove it
afterwards and we're going to run a uh
goang I think it's actually called goang
uh we're just going to run a
container is it is it go I might be
go.go let me go
see let want see if I have a goink Comm
what is it what is the container you
guys
know I thought it was goink it might
have to be I might have to do the dark r
on it I think I might have to do dark R
because it's because it's p man
yeah I think I have to do dark
R is it Go Das go I think I have to do
I have to I think I have to do
this I don't
know call Docker container let me go
look it up really quick sorry guys for
missing this hub. doer there it is hub.
dark.com
all right
[Music]
so how about
do.com uncore
is it going to go wi get no I'm talking
about running a pod man
thing this is driving me
nuts uh this is the wrong the my dam is
not
running oh oh God that's right I
rebooted sorry about
that
podman Adit no
was it
start no what is it I don't I'm I'm a
Docker guy I have been I hate Docker so
I'm trying to use pod man I'm
sucking is it machine in it it's pod man
machine something
right what is it
um I don't remember mine's been
running this is this is a podman thing
that's why I don't remember it you have
to do it on the
pman it's in the
message oh oh
God it is machine
start yeah there it is I'm so
dumb I am totally dumb hey hi Ian how
you doing yeah I can't believe I miss
that oh
well um hopefully my machine is not
going to start dropping frames or
something so all right here we go go I
think it should be much easier
now yeah look at
that that was a lot easier all right so
there's no VI over here right there's no
V or VI so you have to studio app to
install
um them you can actually you could just
do Neo at that point app install
neim I think it's
neim
right what oh no apt update this
yeah I know it's been a while it's the
holiday pman Works no it just it
connects automatically podman connects
automatically to The Container when you
run it that's what's happening yeah you
can SSH but you don't need to you can
SSH to the to the backing BM if you want
too it's pretty cool so anyway
um uh appt install
neovim yes
um and uh uh you know if you want to
pull down your stuff you can um I mean
how much time we
got we got two or three minutes left
here so let me go try this see how fast
I can do it get wait do we have get
clone Here app install get if you do
this make sure you don't throw your
container away because you'll lose all
your work unless you're synchronize it
so um all right so get add wait wait
wait um AB is no that's not going to
work either I'm just going to do get get
clone I'm going to use HTP on on purpose
people because I don't want to have to
authenticate um and I'm going to clone
my do
files okay and then I'm going to CD into
my DOT files and I'm going to run/
setup uh and then I'm going to say tmok
see I'm going to say exact bash
DL and now yay I have my Bash
okay so there's my whole environment and
I have get and GitHub already set up in
BM and everything so um you know you
could also if you want to do GH you can
do off uh GH
off uh
login okay so sudu let's see appt
install
um
GH and it'll get you the GH tool GH off
login
uh Enterprise
https uh and I'm going to hit htps and
it's going to give me some stuff give me
a second here it's going to give me my
authentication thing log in with my web
browser it gives me a token to paste in
then I go paste the thing in and I hit
enter and now I can do GH repo clone or
cop sorry do yeah DH repo clone which
I'm not going to
do uh right now and yeah even if you can
see credentials that's not that is no
longer a valid code just in case you're
wondering um and whoops wrong bre all
right so then what now now what now you
can start writing go code so yeah you
can CD into wherever doesn't matter
because I'm rout make directory app CD
app uh go mod
andit uh go modit github.com rvx rob
SL uh coding from the get
go um yep and then VI may.
go P main now I don't have any of my
other stuff here yet in fact I could get
it I could do plug
install uh and that'll install all of my
stuff my vimo will get updated
um and then we can actually also in
doing that um we can uh do some other
stuff here so yeah we need to fix to go
run install binaries so we go install
binaries uh I'm glad we're doing this
because some of you on the terminal are
going to need to do these things this
does take a while to run um and this is
a good example of doing it I mean if you
if you you'd have to do all of these
things on a new system anyway so I'm
just doing them
inside of a container and because the
container has not been set up um it does
always take a little while for these
things to download and and install um
but you know once they're there you're
you're good to
go it had to be said it had to be said
my friends um and on that note we are
about ready to be done so
um we are about ready to be done and
you're like yeah just in time to be
saved for Mr Rob's puns so we're going
to have a lot of worse puns coming I'm
promising you yeah and uh and we're
going to write our first hello world
program and stuff in the next hour um
we're actually going to probably finish
two or three um activities in the next
hour so uh I'm going to go ahead and and
stop the video right now and if you want
to continue you can come back after this
and um we'll the next thing we're going
to be doing is actually writing our very
first program and I'm going to take
about a five or 10- minute copy break
and I'm going to end the video and start
it uploading right now all right talk to
you in a bit